Now that you know how to create a variety of NumPy arrays,
现在你已经知道要怎么创建不同的 NumPy 数组了
let's see how NumPy allows us to effectively manipulate the data within them.
我们来看怎么用 NumPy 高效处理数据
NumPy arrays are mutable,
NumPy 数组是可变的
meaning the elements in them can be changed after the array has been created.
也就是说 数组创建完毕后 其中的元素还可以更改
NumPy arrays can also be sliced in many different ways.
NumPy 的数组还有多种切片方式
This allows us to achieve any subset of the array we want.
方便我们获取任意数组子集
You'll often use slicing to separate data.
切片常用于分离数据
For example, when dividing a dataset into training,
比如把数据集分割成训练集
cross validation, and testing sets.
交叉验证集和测试集
We will start by looking how the elements of
我们先来看
a NumPy array can be accessed or modified by indexing.
怎么用索引访问或修改 NumPy 数组的元素
Let's create a rank one array that contains integers from one to five.
首先 创建一个秩为 1 的数组 该数组包含 1 到 5 五个整数
Elements can be accessed by specifying
要访问元素
their positions using indices inside square brackets.
我们可以在方括号里填写索引 从而指定其位置
Positive indices are used to specify positions from the beginning of the array.
正索引指定的位置是从数组开头开始数起的
Notice that to access the first element in the array,
注意 访问数组的第一个元素
we have to use index zero not one.
要用的索引是 0 而不是 1
We can also use negative indices to specify positions from the end of the array.
我们也可以用负索引来指定从数组末端往回数的位置
Notice that the same element can be accessed using both negative and positive integers.
注意 同一个元素既可以用正整数访问 也可以用负整数访问
As mentioned earlier, positive indices are
重申一遍 正索引
used to access elements from the beginning of the array,
用于访问从数组开头数起的元素
while negative indices are used to access elements from the end of the array.
而负索引用于访问从数组末端往回数起的元素
Now, let's see how we can modify the elements in an array.
现在 我们来看怎么修改数组里的元素
We can do this by accessing the element we want to change,
要实现该操作 我们得访问要修改的元素
and then reassigning it using the equal sign.
然后用等号为其重新赋值
Let's modify the array X we just created.
现在来修改我们刚创建的数组 x
We can change the fourth element in X from four to 20.
我们可以把 x 的第四个元素从 4 改为 20
We can also access and modify specific elements of rank two in NumPy arrays.
我们也可以访问并修改秩为 2 的 NumPy 数组的特定元素
The only difference is that we need to provide
唯一的区别在于
two indices separated by a comma inside the square brackets.
我们需要在方括号内提供两个索引 索引之间以逗号隔开
Here's a three by three array containing the integers from one to nine.
这是个 3 x 3 整数矩阵 其元素为 1 到 9
Let's access some elements in that array.
我们来访问数组的一些元素
Remember that zero, comma,
记住 [0 , 0]
zero refers to the element in the first row and the first column, which is one.
指的是第一列第一行的元素 也就是 1
Elements in rank two arrays can also be modified in the same way.
要修改秩为 2 的数组的元素 方法也是一样的
We can change the zero, comma,
我们可以把 x 里 [0 , 0] 上的元素
zero element, in X from one to 20 like this.
像这样从 1 改为 20
Now that we know how to access and modify elements in an array,
知道了如何访问和修改数组里的元素
let's take a look at how we can add and delete elements.
现在我们来看怎么添加和删除元素
We can delete elements using NumPy's delete function.
要删除元素 我们可以用 NumPy 的函数 delete
This function takes in an array,
该函数接受的参数有一个数组
list of indices to delete,
要删除的索引列表
and an axis to delete from.
以及要删除的轴
For rank one arrays,
秩为 1 的数组
the axis keyword is not required.
不需要输入轴的关键字 axis
For rank two arrays,
秩为 2 的数组
axis zero is used to select rows and axis one is used to select columns.
设 axis 为 0 则选中行 设 axis 为 1 则选中列
Let's see some examples.
我们来看一些例子
Here is a rank one array,
这是个秩为 1 的数组
we can delete the first and last element of X like this.
像这样就可以删除 x 的第一个和最后一个元素了
And here is a rank 2 array,
这是个秩为 2 的数组
and delete the first and last column of Y like this.
像这样就可以删除 Y 的第一列和最后一列了
We can add values to NumPy arrays using the append function.
我们可以用函数 append 来给 NumPy 数组追加值
This function takes in an array,
该函数接受的参数有一个数组
a list of elements to append,
要追加的元素列表
and the axis to append it on.
以及要追加元素的轴
Let's see some examples.
我们来看一些例子
We can append an element six to this rank one array like this.
我们可以像这样给秩为 1 的数组追加元素 6
And we can append multiple elements,
我们也可以追加多个元素
say seven and eight in a list like this.
比如像这样 输入由 7 和 8 组成的列表
In a rank two array,
对于秩为 2 的数组
we can append a new row containing 10,
我们可以追加一个由
11, and 12 like this.
10、11、12 组成的新行 就像这样
And we can append a new column containing 10,
也可以追加一个由
11, 12 like this.
10、11、12 组成的新列 像这样
Notice that when appending rows or columns to rank two NumPy arrays,
注意 在给秩为 2 的 NumPy 数组追加行或列时
the rows and columns must have the correct shape to match the shape of the array.
新行或新列的形状必须和数组形状相符
Now, let's see how we can insert values into NumPy arrays.
现在我们来看怎么将值插入 NumPy 数组中
We can use the insert function for this,
我们可以用函数 insert
which takes in an array,
该函数的参数有 一个数组
index, elements, and axis.
索引、元素和轴
This inserts the given list of elements to the array right before
要插入的元素会出现在
the given index along the specified axis. Here's a rank one array.
给定索引之前、给定轴之上 这是个秩为 1 的数组
We can insert the integers three and four between these elements two and five like this.
我们可以像这样把 3 和 4 插到 2 和 5 这两个元素之间
In this rank two array,
对于这个秩为 2 的数组
we can insert a row between this first and last row like this.
我们可以像这样在第一行和最后一行之间插入一行
And insert a column full of fives between the first and second column like this.
或者在第一列和第二列之间插入一个元素都为 5 的列 像这样
NumPy also allows us to stack NumPy arrays on top of each other or side by side.
NumPy 还能堆叠 NumPy 数组 堆叠可以是垂直的 也可以是水平的
The stacking is done using either NumPy's Vstack for
用 NumPy 的函数 vstack 可以进行垂直堆叠
vertical stacking or Hstack function for horizontal stacking.
用 hstack 可以进行水平堆叠
It's important to note that in order to stack arrays,
注意 数组堆叠时
the shape of the arrays must match.
形状必须匹配
Consider this rank one and rank two array X and Y.
我们来看这个秩为 1 的数组 x 和秩为 2 的数组 Y
We can stack X on top of Y with Vstack like this.
我们可以像这样用 vstack 把 x 堆叠在 Y 上
And we can stack X on the right of Y with Hstack like this.
也可以像这样用 hstack 把 x 堆叠到 Y 的右边
We need to reshape X to match the shape of Y before stacking it horizontally.
但是在水平堆叠之前 我们要调整 x 的形状 使其与 Y 的形状相匹配